"Lion’s Mane Mushroom Powder
for Brain Health"
I've talked about the benefits
of nitrate-rich vegetables
for improving
cognitive function.
Do any other vegetables
stand out?
Mushrooms are in a class
of their own-literally,
in fact, a kingdom
of their own-
belonging to the fungi
rather than plant kingdom.
Epidemiological studies
in Japan, Singapore,
Norway, the Netherlands,
and the United States
have found associations
between mushroom consumption
and superior
cognitive function.
Compared to people
who don't eat mushrooms,
those in the highest category
of mushroom intake in the U.S.
had a higher performance
on various cognitive tests,
and that highest intake
was only averaging
about one mushroom a day.
This result appeared
to be independent
of other dietary
and lifestyle factors.
The researchers suggested
it may be the unique mushroom
antioxidant ergothioneine
that I've profiled previously,
and indeed,
a study out of France found
blood ergothioneine levels
associated with lower odds
of cognitive decline.
The U.S. research team
suggested
that "regular
mushroom consumption
may reduce the risk
of cognitive decline,"
but it was just
a cross-sectional snapshot
in time, so you don't know
which came first.
Japanese researchers performed
a prospective study
following more than
10,000 men and women
aged 65 and older
for about six years.
In that time, about 1 in 12
was diagnosed with dementia.
What seemed to lower risk
of falling into that faction?
Mushroom consumption.
Compared to those
who ate mushrooms
less than once a week,
those who ate mushrooms
three or more times a week
had a 19 percent lower chance
of becoming demented.
The cross-sectional study
in Singapore
found 57 percent lower odds
of having cognitive impairment
among those eating
more than two portions a week.
As always, though,
cause and effect
can only be established
with interventional trials.
A six-month randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
randomizing older men and women
to plain white
button mushrooms or placebo
found no difference
in cognitive function,
but the dose was only
about 200 mg a day
of dried mushroom powder.
That's the fresh weight
equivalent of less than
a quarter of a single small
mushroom a day.
This enabled the researchers to
stuff the mushrooms
into capsules so they could
be blinded against placebo
but offers little insight
into what even a single daily
serving of mushrooms might do,
which would constitute fifty
times the studied dose.
What about fancier fungi,
like the gourmet edible
mushroom called lion's mane
(or less palatably,
bearded tooth fungus).
In 2009, a pilot study found
that older men and women
diagnosed with mild cognitive
impairment randomized
to a few grams of dried lion's
mane mushroom powder a day
experienced
a significant improvement
in cognitive function
compared to placebo
starting as soon as month two.
Despite the promising results,
an attempt
to replicate the results
wasn't published
for another decade.
Researchers tried
about three grams
of powdered lion's
mane mushroom a day
in cognitively
healthy older adults.
A significant
improvement over placebo
was found in one of three
cognitive measures.
Finally, in 2020,
a study was published
on lion's mane mushroom for
early Alzheimer's disease.
A nearly year-long
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of about a gram a day
of dried and powdered
lab-grown lion's mane
sadly found no cognitive
benefits compared to placebo,
but it did perhaps improve
the ability to perform
activities of daily living, a
measure of independence.